Guide to the Jerome Zeifman papers, 1960-1977 MS2167
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jerome Zeifman papers
1960-1977
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Zeifman, Jerome M.
MS2167
7.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains materials collected by Jerome Ziefman (1925-2010) in the course of his work as counsel and later chief counsel to the Committee on the Judiciary of the United States House of Representatives. The material dates from 1960-1977 and contains reports, memoranda, correspondence, notes, legal documents, government documents, publications, clippings, and audio recordings.
Restrictions on Access
Regarding use of the diaries and recordings found in series 1, researchers are allowed to use the diaries and recordings, but may not make reproductions, publish, or even quote from the diaries or recordings without written permission of the donor or his heirs and assigns. When requesting the diaries or recordings to use for research, please ask the SCRC staff to provide a copy of the Restricted Use Agreement for you to sign. You must sign this form before gaining access to the diaries and recordings.
Staff alert: Here is the Restricted Use Agreement to share with researchers
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Jerome Zeifman in 1999 and 2000.
Historical or Biographical Note
Jerome M. Zeifman (1925-2010) was born in Mineola, New York. He attended Harvard University and received a law degree from New York University. During World War II he served as a naval communications officer. Zeifman operated a private law practice in Nyack, New York prior to working for the Committee on the Judiciary of the United States House of Representatives.
Zeifman served as counsel (1961-1973) and general counsel (1973-74) to the Judiciary Committee. Initially Zeifman was hired to advise the Judiciary Committee on interstate taxation. Zeifman worked closely with Peter W. Rodino and was involved with Rodino's work on policy related to substance abuse and drug use. As general counsel Zeifman was involved with the Committee's work related to Watergate, the impeachment of Richard Nixon, and the confirmations of Gerald Ford and Nelson Rockefeller. Zeifman retired from the Committee staff in 1974 to teach law at the University of Santa Clara.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains materials collected by Jerome Ziefman (1925-2010) in the course of his work as counsel and later chief counsel to the Committee on the Judiciary of the United States House of Representatives. The material dates from 1960-1977 and contains reports, memoranda, correspondence, notes, legal documents, government documents, publications, clippings, and audio recordings.
The collection contains Zeifman's personal diary, correspondence, and notes as well as documents compiled, produced, and used by the Committee on the Judiciary. The collection deals primarily with issues related to the Watergate Scandal, the resignation of Spiro Agnew, the impeachment of President Nixon, the confirmation of Gerald Ford as President, the confirmation of Nelson Rockefeller as Vice President, and the pardoning of Richard Nixon by Gerald Ford. The materials also reflect the inner workings of the Judiciary Committee and contains information about the employment of other Committee staff who later rose to national prominence, including Hillary Rodham Clinton, Bernard Nussbaum, John Doar, and William Weld.
Documents produced and compiled by Zeifman during his employment as Counsel and Chief Counsel for the Judiciary Committee reflect his working relationship with other staff members of the Judiciary Committee staff, members of Congress, other Congressional staffers. Zeifman's work with Congressman Peter Rodino is especially well documented. Also documented are interactions between the Judiciary Committee and President Nixon's staff, Nixon's legal counsel, and other executive branch employees.
Collection Organization
The records are arranged in three series: Personal Papers, Historical file, and Stenographic minutes.
Arrangement reflects the original order maintained by Jerome Zeifman when possible. Files are often broad groupings of documents that reflect usage by Zeifman and the Judiciary Committee during a certain period of time.
Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974 -- Personal Narrative; Trials (Impeachment) -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974; Diaries; Audiotapes; Zeifman, Jerome M.; Ford, Gerald R. (1913-2006); Rodino, Peter W., Jr., 1909-2005; United States. Congress. House. Committee on the Judiciary; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous)
- Personal papers, 1960-1974; Series 1; 2 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 14, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains personal correspondence, diaries, audiorecordings and other papers of Jerome Zeifman. The material dates from 1960-1975. The series includes tape recordings of Zeifman's diaries and typed transcripts. Note that researchers wishing to view the materials in this series must first be approved by the donor and sign a written agreement to not quote or publish from these materials without first gaining the permission of the donor.
  - Personal file 1970--Zeifman, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal file 1971--Zeifman (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal file 1972--Zeifman (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Personal file 1973--Zeifman (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal file--Zeifman (Releases), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal file 1974--Zeifman (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Book draft, proposal, notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clipping, note, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photograph: Jerome Zeifman and Tom Railsback (Box 1, Folder 9)
    General note
    Text on photograph: "L-R Rep. Tom Railsback (R-Ill) General Counsel Jerry Zeifman"
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [1/6], 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [2/6], 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [3/6], 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [4/6], 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [5/6], 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - An Impeachment Diary by Jerome M. Zeifman [6/6], 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Diary: Audiocassette #1, 11/27/1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    "1 / Diary #1 Ends on Nov. 27"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #2, 07/1974 --08/1974 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    "2 / July 31- Aug 1 etc. The true story of Watergate"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #3, 12/06/1973 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    "2 [sic] / Diary #2 ends Dec 6, 1973"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #4, 12/06/1973 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    "3 / Diary #3 Dec. 6, 1973"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #5, 02/03/1974 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    "4 / Ends February 3, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #6, 02/15/1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    "5 / Ends February 15, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #7, 01/21/1974 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    "6 / Diary Ends Jan 21, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #8, 01/21/1974 --01/24/1974 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    "6A / Jan 21, 1974-Begins (cont) Ends Jan 24, 1974 Diary"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #9, 01/24/1974 --01/29/1974 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    "7 / Begins Jan 24 (cont) Diary, Ends Jan 29, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #10, 01/29/1974 --02/06/1974 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    "8 / Diary Begins Jan 29 (Cont) Ends Feb 6"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #11, 02/09/1974 --02/15/1974 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    "9 / Diary Feb 9 Ends Feb 15"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #12, 02/15/1974 --02/20/1974 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    "10 / Diary Begins Feb 15 (cont) Ends Feb 20"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #13, 02/20/1974 --03/03/1974 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    "11 / Diary Begins Feb 20 (cont) Ends March 3"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #14, 03/04/1974 --03/12/1974 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    "12 / Diary Begins Mar 4, 1974 Ends March 12, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #15, 03/11/1974 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    "13 / Diary Begins March 11, 1974 (cont)"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #16, 03/20/1974 --04/02/1974 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    "14 / Begins March 20 (cont) End April 2"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #17, 04/02/1974 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    "15 / Begins April 2 1974 (cont)"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #18, 04/30/1974 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    "16 / Diary Begins April 20, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #19, 05/07/1974 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    "17 / Diary May 7, 1974 continued"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #20, 05/09/1974 --05/27/1974 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    "18 / Diary May 9, 1974 (continued) Ends May 27"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #21, 06/04/1974 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    "19 / Diary Begins June 4, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #22, 06/04/1974 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    "20 / Diary Ends June 4, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #23, 06/04/1974 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    "20A / Side #2 of Tape #20 (unintelligible on original tape) Ends June 4, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #24, 06/1974 --06/22/1974 (Box 13, Folder 24)
    "21 / Diary Begins June ? Ends June 22"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #25, 06/22/1974 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    "22 / Begins June 22, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #26, 06/29/1974 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    "23 / Diary Begins June 29, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #27 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    "Side #1 of Tape 24"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #28, 06/30/1974 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    "24 / Diary Begins June 30, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #29, 07/08/1974 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    "25 / Begins July 8, 1974"
  - Diary: Audiocassette #30, 07/16/1974 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    "26 / Diary Begins July 16, 1974 (note the beginning of the next tape got erased. For explanation see #2 side of [illegible]."
  - Diary: Audiocassette #31, 08/05/1974 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    "27 / Diary August 4, 1974 [illegible]"
  - Stenorette tape magazine (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Stenorette tape magazine (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Stenorette tape magazine (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Audiotape (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Historical file, 1961-1977; Series 2; 4 Linear feet (Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10, Box 2)
  This series contains reports, memoranda, correspondence, notes, legal documents, publications, clippings and other documents. The material dates from 1970-77, and deals primarily with issues related the Watergate scandal, the resignation of Spiro Agnew, the impeachment of President Nixon, the confirmation of Gerald Ford to be President, the confirmation of Nelson Rockefeller to be Vice President, the efforts of Gerald Ford (as majority leader) to impeach Supreme Court Justice William O. Douglass, and prior efforts to impeach seven other federal judges. Whenever possible, original folder titles have been maintained.
  - Peter W. Rodino, Jr. Historical file (Ford), 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Impeachment--Legal materials, 1966-1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The September 15th White House Conversation: Cause for the Impeachment of Richard Nixon and an Investigation of the Department of Justice", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gerald Ford confirmation--Background [1/2], 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Gerald Ford confirmation--Background [2/2], 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Historical file, 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Watergate misc., 1973 May-1973 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "A Report to the Special Prosecutor on Certain Aspects of the Watergate Affair" ACLU, 1973 June 18 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jerome Zeifman clippings historical file, 08/1973 --04/1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 10/1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ford confirmation historical file, 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gerald Ford--Resolutions, bills, and press releases by PWR, Jr., 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Historical file, 09/1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jerome Zeifman historical record (Ford) [1/2], 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Jerome Zeifman historical record (Ford) [2/2], 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Peter W. Rodino historical file (Ford) [1/2], 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Peter W. Rodino historical file (Ford) [2/2], 10/1973 --12/1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--January 1970 and before, 10/1973 --01/1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Press releases 1974, 10/1973 --07/1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Congressional research service report: "Analysis of the Philosophy and Voting Record of Gerald R. Ford, Nominee for Vice President of the United States", 10/25/1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Inquiry count, 10/30/1973 --08/20/1974 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "The Offenses of Richard M. Nixon: A Lawyer's Guide for the People of the United States of America", 11/1973 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Materials for Ford confirmation hearing, 11/1973 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Peter W. Rodino, Jr. historical file, 11/1973 --12/1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chairman Peter W. Rodino, Jr., 11/1973 --12/1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pardon, 11/1973 --09/1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Congressional research service report: "Views Held by Gerald R. Ford with Regard to Congressional-Executive Relations", 11/06/1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Jerome Zeifman historical record, 03/1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Impeachment inquiry--Peter W. Rodino, Jr., 12/1973 --03/1974 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Gerald Ford's pardon of Richard Nixon, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Watergate and the Law: political campaigns and presidential power / Ralph K. Winter, Jr., 1974; MS2167 Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - [John M. Doar, New York City School Board], 1974; MS2167 Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Memo: Disposition of Watergate-related materials / [by] Stan Bach, 1974 November 01; MS2167 Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Legal History of Wiretapping Authority in Law Enforcement Agencies / [Congressional Research Service, The Library of Congress], 1974-01-04 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Historical file, 01/1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--February 1974 [1/2], 02/1974 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--February 1974 [2/2], 02/1974 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Historical file, 02/1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hearings Before the Committee on the Judiciary House of Representatives Ninety-third Congress, 02/1974 --07/1974 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--March 1974 [1/2], 03/1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--March 1974 [2/2], 03/1974 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--April 1974, 04/1974 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 04/1974 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Historical file, 04/1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - "Examination of President Nixon's Tax Returns for 1969 through 1972 Prepared for the Joint Committee on Internal Revenue Taxation...", 04/03/1974 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--May 1974, 05/1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Historical file, 05/1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - A Treatise On Federal Impeachment / by Alex Simpson, 1970; MS2167 Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 05/1974 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Impeachment inquiry file--june 1974, 06/1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 06/1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Historical file, 06/1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - F.B.I. Counter intelligence programs, 06/1974 --11/1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file--Memorandum: Report on impoundment of funds, 06/12/1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 07/1974 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 07/1974 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Historical file, 07/1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Comparison of passages from "Transcripts of Eight Recorded Presidential Conversations" by the Committee on the Judiciary House of Representatives, 07/09/1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Brief on Behalf of the President of the United States Richard Nixon to the Committee on the Judiciary Ninety-third Congress U.S. House of Represenatatives, 07/19/1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Full committee notice of meeting, 07/23/1974 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Special historical file, 07/24/1974 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 08/1974 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Nelson D. Rockefeller, 08/1974 --10/1974 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, 09/1974 --11/1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - "Big Brother and the Holding Company: The World Behind Watergate" page proofs, 10/28/1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Historical file, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - An Analysis of the Constitutional Standard for Presidential Impeachment (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Impeachment inquiry historical file, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The EOB Tape of June 20, 1972: report on a technical investigation / conducted by the U.S. District Court of Columbia by the Advisory Panel on White House Tapes, 1974; MS2167 Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Stenographic Minutes, 1974; Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 10, Box 11, Box 12)
  This series contains stenographic minutes of the proceedings of the Committee on Judiciary of the United States House of Representatives. The material dates from January through July 1974. The minutes are unedited and unrevised.
  Bib #
  6810792
  - Report of the Proceedings: Hearing held before Committee on the Judiciary investigatory powers of Committee on the Judiciary with respect to its impeachment inquiry, vol. 1, 1974 January 31; MS2167 Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Briefing by Staff Vol. 1, 02/05/1974 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Briefing by Staff Vol. 1, 02/14/1974 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Briefing by Staff Vol. 1, 02/22/1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Briefing by Staff Vol. 1, 03/05/1974 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Committee Business--Executive Session Vol. 1, 03/12/1974 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Impeachment Briefing Vol. 1, 03/20/1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Impeachment Briefing Vol. 2, 03/21/1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Committee Business Vol. 1, 03/26/1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Impeachment Briefing Vol. 1, 04/04/1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Impeachment Briefing Vol. 1, 04/08/1974 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Impeachment Briefing Vol. 1, 04/11/1974 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment Meeting Vol. 1, 04/25/1974 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Procedures Vol. 1, 05/01/1974 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Impeachment Meeting Vol. 1, 05/01/1974 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Impeachment Meeting Vol. 1, 05/02/1974 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Impeachment Inquiry--Executive Session Vol. 1, 05/09/1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 1, 05/09/1974 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 2, 05/14/1974 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 1, 07/24/1974 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 2, 07/25/1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 3, 07/26/1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 5, 07/29/1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Impeachment Inquiry Vol. 6, 07/30/1974 (Box 12, Folder 8)